<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief history of the rise, growth, reign, supports, and sodain fatal foyl of popery, during the three years and an half of James the Second, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland Together with a description of the six popish pillars, the Anabaptists, Presbyterians, Quakers, Independents, Roman-Catholicks, &amp; popish church-men. The perpetual addressers of the King.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229470</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899219</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899219</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152569</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2305:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief history of the rise, growth, reign, supports, and sodain fatal foyl of popery, during the three years and an half of James the Second, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland Together with a description of the six popish pillars, the Anabaptists, Presbyterians, Quakers, Independents, Roman-Catholicks, &amp; popish church-men. The perpetual addressers of the King.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author: and are to be sold by most booksellers in London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Anabaptists, Presbyterians, Quakers," and "Independents, .. popish-churchmen." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2305 lacks the bottom half of page 33.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152569:1"/>
            <p>A Brief HISTORY OF THE Riſe, Growth, Reign, Supports, and ſodain fatal Foyl of POPERY, during the three Years and an half of <hi>JAMES</hi> the SECOND, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Deſcription of the Six Popiſh Pillars,</p>
            <p>THE
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Presbyterians,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quakers,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Independants,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Roman-Catholicks,</hi> &amp;</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Popiſh Church-men.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The perpetual Addreſſers of the King.</p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. XXIV. ver. 21.</bibl>
               <p>My Son, Fear thou the Lord and the King: And meddle not with them that are given to Change.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author: And are to be Sold by moſt Bookſellers in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:152569:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152569:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN HISTORY OF THE Riſe, Growth, Reign, Supports, and ſodain fatal Foyl of POPERY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>RAiling Accuſation</hi> was ſuch a thing as <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel <hi>durſt not uſe againſt the Devil,</hi> (Jud. 9.) But when <hi>Men ſpeak Evil,</hi> in ſuch caſes by ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe only, <hi>of things which they know not, and that of Dignities,</hi> (ver. 10. 8.) Then <hi>woe unto Them,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>for that they are in the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and are greedily running after the error of</hi> Balaam <hi>for reward,</hi> and are threatned that <hi>They ſhall periſh in the gainſaying of Korah,</hi> (ver. 11.) Theſe <hi>are ſpots in our feasts.</hi> Now in all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and Publick Affairs, it is the Duty of all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to perform all Offices and acts of duty with utmoſt Charity, as They tender the wellfare of the common good of Their Country wherein They inhabit: But of all ſuch National Affairs, none call louder for acts of pure Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, than the Election of grave and wiſe Magiſtrates and Councellors, who are to ſit at the Helm, in order to manage the great Councils of a whole Kingdom. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to hear of Schiſms and Factions in ſuch caſes, ſavors
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152569:3"/>exceedingly of the ſpirit and temper of <hi>Cain,</hi> who <hi>ſlew his Brother,</hi> and why? <hi>But becauſe his own works were evil, and his Brothers good,</hi> (Joh. 3.12.). Was it any wrong to the <hi>City of London,</hi> that it had yet More men of Reputation, to ſtand as <hi>Candidates</hi> to be Elected Members of <hi>Parliament,</hi> to ſerve for that moſt famous and Metropolitan City of the Kingdom, and that over and above, and beſides what had ſerved immediately before? Surely no, but rather it is for the glory of that Noble City, that it hath ſuch variety of Choice. But was it ſo, that the Reputation and fame, of the wiſdom and vertue of the <hi>New Members,</hi> did make the loudeſt noiſe above the <hi>Old Ones;</hi> yet why ſhould this breed ſo much the <hi>more envy?</hi> What needed <hi>Malitious Lies</hi> to be ſtrown into the Vulgar Ears, in order to ſuppreſs the noiſe of Vertue and Honour? Or what needed the Clamours of <hi>Anabaptiſts, Presbyterians, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational-Men,</hi> that cry'd down the choice by ſuch Men as They ſaid, <hi>[would bring in King</hi> James <hi>again to Reign over us?]</hi> That <hi>Popery</hi> is one of the <hi>greateſt Annoyances</hi> that can befall this Kingdom, and the <hi>bittereſt Pill</hi> that can be preſcribed for the Subjects, here, to take, is a Doctrine paſt Diſpute. And to be an Inſtrument to introduce ſuch <hi>Members of Parliament,</hi> as ſhall purpoſely endeavour to ſet up ſuch a Prince as certainly will Eſtabliſh <hi>Popery</hi> in all that ever He can do, ſavors neither of <hi>Charity</hi> towards this <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Kingdom of England,</hi> nor of <hi>Piety towards God.</hi> What King <hi>James</hi> hath done, is too well known. And we cannot ſay, but the Sin of the People, hath juſtly deſerved all that hath befallen us; and not only ſo, but alſo the whole of all thoſe fears upon us, that they ſhould have come to paſs even as we feared. And what the wrath of God, becauſe of our Sins, hath yet behind, to throw upon us, God knows! And we may juſtly dread! However, it becomes not us to ſpeak evil of Kings, eſpecially ſo nearly Related unto ſuch, by whoſe means we have received good things. Leaving therefore that wickedneſs to be acted only by the wicked and deviliſh Railers; let us only for the good of this Church and Kingdom, make a ſtrict inquiry out of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152569:3"/>the <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Weekly Gazettes, who</hi> and <hi>what</hi> They were, who were the greateſt promoters of all theſe Evil things, for the ſake of which we cry out ſo much againſt King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>February</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> 1684. King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. Died. And on the ſame day was Proclaimed <hi>James</hi> the II. as His only Brother, and Heir. And afterwards King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> having confirmed all Officers in Place as were before, came into the Privy-Council Chamber, and ſpake, ſaying to this effect as follows; <hi>[That He would follow His Brothers Example in Clemency and Tenderneſs to His People. That He would endeavour to preſerve the Government both in Church and State, as then it was by Law Eſtabliſhed. That He would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways take care to Defend and Support the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England. <hi>That He would never invade any Man's Property. That He would go as far as any Man in preſerving the Defence of this Nation in all its juſt Rights and Liberties.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Speech by the King's Command was made Publick. How He hath kept His Royal Word, God knows, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh not me to ſay.</p>
            <p>On <hi>February the 11th.</hi> came in the firſt Addreſs from <hi>Portſmouth</hi> Garriſon, and the Society of <hi>Lincolns Inn,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating His Majeſties Acceſſion to the Throne, and promiſing Obedience. And henceforwards came in more <hi>February</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> from <hi>Ipſwich:</hi> The <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Company, Merchants of the <hi>Levant:</hi> The Biſhop and Clergy of <hi>London:</hi> The <hi>Inner-Temple, Middle-Temple London, Grays-Inn, Portſmouth</hi> Corporation, <hi>Wells</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire, Weſtminſter,</hi> &amp;c. And on the ſame day was King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> Buried Privately at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in the Evening.</p>
            <p>Henceforward followed Addreſſes from all Counties and moſt of the Great Towns all over <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and from moſt Parts of His Majeſties Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And Ambaſſadors from all the Neighbouring King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and States did Congratulate.</p>
            <p>On <hi>April</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> 1685. King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> with <hi>Mary</hi> His Queen, were both Crowned at <hi>Westminster</hi> with great Pomp and State; at what time His Majeſty took
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152569:4"/>His Oath to do all things according to what he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore promiſed, on the day he came firſt to be King.</p>
            <p>Now, preſently after His Majeſty came to the Crown, He began to ſhew Himſelf a <hi>Papist,</hi> and openly went to <hi>Maſs</hi> at His Palace at St. <hi>James</hi>'s. Notwithſtanding which, infinite numbers of Addreſſes of Congratulation were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually coming in unto His Coronation, and after.</p>
            <p>On the <hi>23d.</hi> of <hi>April</hi> alſo met the <hi>Parliament</hi> called in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Which being Met, did greatly Congratulate His Majeſties Acceſſion to the Throne, with promiſes of much Obedience. And this <hi>Parliament</hi> made an Act to confirm and ſecure the Proteſtant Religion as it was then Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by <hi>Arch-biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and did promiſe in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the King, to do their beſt to Extirpate <hi>Fanataciſm,</hi> as in thoſe days They counted and called the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> Met at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster.</hi> At what time His Majeſty renewed His Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made at His firſt coming to the Crown, <hi>viz. To main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>and the Property of the Subject.</hi> And withal gave notice of <hi>Argyle</hi> Landed in <hi>Scotland.</hi> And immediately the Lords firſt, and then the Commons, were thankful for the King's Speech, and promiſed to aſſiſt him againſt <hi>Argyle;</hi> who coming in well furniſhed with Armour, Ships and Men, as his caſe ſtood, yet met with ſmall Encouragement, managed his buſineſs very meanly, fought Cowardly, and in a Month's time was utterly rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and broken, Himſelf taken, his Son <hi>Charles</hi> (as was thought) Dead, and all his Company broken. He was executed on the Firſt of <hi>July,</hi> 1685.</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> with two or three ſmall Veſſels, loaded with a good quantity of Arms, and a few Men, Landed at <hi>Lyme</hi> in <hi>Dorſet-ſhire.</hi> But againſt him alſo the <hi>Parliament</hi> unanimouſly joyned with the King, and giving Him Money to raiſe an Army, Declared the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> Traytor by <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi> But the Duke encreaſing his Army mightily at <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-ſhire;</hi> managed his Affairs with a notable Conduct and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152569:4"/>Courage: But finally at <hi>Wells</hi> his Army beginning to Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and to break out into Debauchery, he ſoon after Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in a Pitch't Battel, ſome Three miles from <hi>Bridgewa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> where being worſted for want of good Horſe-men. His Foot fought well, until overpowered by the King's Cannons, and His Horſe and Foot all together upon them, the Field was loſt; and ſoon after the Duke was Taken, <hi>July</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> being hid in a Ditch; and being brought to <hi>London,</hi> he was Beheaded on <hi>Tower-Hill:</hi> the <hi>15th.</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1685. But the L—d G—<hi>y</hi> being alſo Taken, Confeſſed the Confederates, and was Saved.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> was a day of Thankſgiving for the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of theſe Victories. <hi>Richard Goodenough</hi> was alſo Taken, who after confeſſed the Accomplices, and ſaved his Life. But <hi>Ferguſon</hi> Eſcaped. Major <hi>Wildman,</hi> Mr. <hi>Speke,</hi> Mr. <hi>Trenchard,</hi> and others. The Lord <hi>Delamere,</hi> Earl of <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and Lord <hi>Brandon,</hi> were made Priſoners.</p>
            <p>From theſe ſtirs of Civil Wars, it came to paſs that a ſtanding Army was ever after kept up by the King, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> Adjourned and Prorogued from time to time, it was paid out of the King's own Revenues. And hence <hi>Popery</hi> encreaſed with much advance, the Queen and one Father <hi>Petre,</hi> much ſpurring on.</p>
            <p>On <hi>November</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> met at <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> according to Adjournment; at what time the King excuſing His Standing-Army kept up, and ſeveral Officers allowed againſt Law, who had not taken the <hi>Teſt.</hi> The <hi>Parliament</hi> not pleaſed herewith, were ſoon Prorogued.</p>
            <p>On <hi>March</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> came forth His Majeſties Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of <hi>General Pardon,</hi> not without many Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>1686. In the Army Popiſh Officers by degrees filled all vacant Places: As alſo <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Popiſh Souldiers mingled in moſt Troops and Companies. <hi>Papiſts</hi> alſo were admitted into Privy-Council; were made Judges, Sheriffs and Juſtices, without taking the <hi>Teſt.</hi> And in <hi>February,</hi> 1686. the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> a great <hi>Papiſt,</hi> Succeeded the Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And the Earl of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152569:5"/>refuſing to become a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> was put out of Place of High Treaſurer.</p>
            <p>On <hi>February</hi> the <hi>24th.</hi> was Publiſhed His Majeſties Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation for Liberty of Conſcience to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and all others as could be truſted in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi> For which the Lords of the Privy-Council of that Kingdom, returned their Thanks. Thus His Majeſty by uniting the <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Intereſt in <hi>Scotland,</hi> began to leſſen the Authority of the then preſent eſtabliſhed Church by Proteſtant Biſhops.</p>
            <p>By this time the Deputy of <hi>Ireland</hi> being become a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and much of the Council; the Army there; the Sheriffs, Judges and Juſtices alſo being moſtly <hi>Popiſh,</hi> or Popiſhly affected, Perſons in Popiſh Rebells Eſtates began to be thruſt out apace, even by Law too, by means of thoſe Judges and Sheriffs; and Popiſh Robbers alſo multiplied, inſomuch as little ſafety for Proteſtants began to appear in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. To quiet which laſt Oppreſſion, came forth the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation from the Deputy, <hi>February</hi> the <hi>21ſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>March</hi> the <hi>18th.</hi> His Majeſty declared His intention to grant <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> unto all Perſons of what Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion ſoever: And the better to Father His deſign, He Prorogued the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>November</hi> 87. And on <hi>April</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> 1687, His Majeſties Declaration to all His loving Subjects for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> came forth.</p>
            <p>Hence followed a crowd of Congratulatory Addreſſes, from all ſorts of Diſſenters. The firſt who began this Holy Dance after His Majeſties Pipe, was a great number of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in and about <hi>London;</hi> and being delivered by ſeveral of the Chief of them, <hi>April</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> was called,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Humble Addreſs of divers of Your Majeſties Subjects in and about the City of</hi> London, <hi>commonly called</hi> Anabaptiſts; <hi>and ſaith,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WE Your Majeſties moſt Humble and Loyal Sabjects, who have been of a Long time great Sufferers, by the ſevere Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Poenal Laws <hi>about matters of Religion, (unto which for Conſcience ſake we could not conform) cannot ſufficiently pay thoſe acknowledgments we owe to Your Majeſty for your late Moſt Gracious</hi> Declaration, <hi>whereby we are not only delivered from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152569:5"/>our paſt Distreſſes, and our Families from Ruine, but are alſo allowed the free exerciſe of our Religion; which is dearer to us than any Worldly Enjoyment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Great Sir, 'tis the fenſe of this invaluable Favour, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit derived to Us from Your Royal Clemency, that compels us once more to Prostrate our ſelves at Your Majestics Feet, with the tender of our most humble Thanks for that Peace and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which both we and all other Diſſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers do now enjoy; and rest confident of, under Your most Gracious Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And being our ſelves most firmly reſolved (as in Conſcience bound) to endeavour to the utmost to give that proof of our Duty and Fidelity to Your Majesty, that you may never have occaſion to repent of Your Princely favour towards us. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but rest confident, That ſuch demonstrations as theſe of Your Majesties tender care of the Proſperity and quiet of Your Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Subjects of all ſorts, (though differing in ſome Sentiments of Religion) will ſo abſolutely command the Hearts of them all, that the only Emulation among them will be, who may approve themſelves best worthy of your Majesties favour, and contribute most towards the glory and happineſs of your Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that God Almighty by pouring out His ſignal Bleſſings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Your Majesty, Your Royal Posterity, Government, and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, will be pleaſed to convince the whole World of the Wiſdom and truth of Your Majesties Sentiments,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>Such were the whileom thoughts of the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> of King <hi>James,</hi> notwithſtanding all His endeavours of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Popery, who appeared in this Addreſs,</p>
            <p>A ſort of People avowing themſelves ſo exceedingly obliged to King <hi>James</hi> for favours done them, that their utmoſt proof of Duty and Fidelity to His Majeſty, can never enough ſatisfie; until <hi>They give Him occaſion never to repent of thoſe princely favours to them.</hi> Which if ſo, then either by this Addreſs they think themſelves bound in Conſcience to <hi>adventure their Lives to Reſtore Him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to His Throne:</hi> (for otherwiſe he muſt needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of His Princely favours to them, in vain beſtowed:) Or elſe they have hereby declared themſelves, a <hi>company of meer empty flattering</hi> Sycophants, <hi>promiſing that which they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152569:6"/>never intended.</hi> And now was it true as is ſaid in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, then are they themſelves <hi>the Men bound to bring in King James,</hi> againſt all ſenſe of the Opinion of His moſt Excellent Majeſty King <hi>William,</hi> in His Declaration expreſſed, and of the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> in declaring the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdom by King <hi>James</hi> to be Forfeited, by reaſon of Miſ-government. Or if otherwiſe, (they ſay what they never intended.) Then is no Credit to be given to any thing they ſay; their Tongues are no Slander; the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> in and about <hi>London,</hi> are a Profligate Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of the Sperm of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leydon</hi> and <hi>Knipperdoling;</hi> a company of branded Hypocrites, never to be believed or truſted.</p>
            <p>They pretend to <hi>have an abſolute Confidence</hi> in King <hi>James,</hi> as to His tender care of the Peace and quiet of His Subjects; they pretend <hi>to ſtrive againſt all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with Emulation,</hi> to <hi>do more for Him than all of them.</hi> They pretend <hi>to be bound to Wiſh, Pray, and Fight, and to do all that may be done,</hi> that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>Prince of</hi> Wales <hi>His Son,</hi> and <hi>His Government may be Bleſſed.</hi> And ſo by conſequence they muſt hold, that all oppoſers ought to be Accurſed. And yet theſe Men cry'd out againſt the late chooſers of <hi>New Members,</hi> [<hi>That they would bring in King</hi> James <hi>again.</hi>]</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>10th.</hi> was preſented to the King, <hi>[The moſt Humble Addreſs of the</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>in Leiceſter-ſhire.]</hi> Wherein theſe alſo acknowledge as the former, <hi>Their Thankfulneſs for the King's Declaration;</hi> and promiſing <hi>moſt faithfully and ambitiouſly to Serve Him with their Obedience and Loyalty in all ways to ihe beſt of His Advantage;</hi> Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>for Him and His Poſterity.</hi> And on <hi>May</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> came in more of the ſame from <hi>Exeter</hi> in the ſame County.</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>17th.</hi> was Preſented the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptists</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire,</hi> Magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>His Majeſties Wiſdom and Clemency with Hyperboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Language,</hi> ſtiling Him the <hi>Rightful Father of His Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions;</hi> Praying Him there may be a <hi>Total Aboliſhment of the Poenal Statutes concerning Religion,</hi> and promiſing Him
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152569:6"/>
               <hi>Exemplary Loyalty;</hi> and concluding with <hi>[Long Live and Reign King</hi> James <hi>the Just.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>21ſt.</hi> was Preſented <hi>[The Humble Addreſs of the</hi> Anabaptiſts <hi>of Stafford, Derby and Nottingham ſhires]</hi> promiſing <hi>Their utmoſt Loyalty to Him,</hi> even unto the <hi>making of Him Great throughout all the World.</hi> And at the ſame time came forth another Addreſs of the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> of <hi>Che-ſhire, Shrop-ſhire</hi> and <hi>Stafford-ſhire,</hi> ſtiling His Majeſty, <hi>A Prince by Heaven deſigned for the higheſt Pattern of Royal Goodneſs and true Policy;</hi> and promiſing to <hi>ſerve Him with ſuch ready Obedience and stedfast Loyalty, to the utmost of their Capacity, in their Station, as it ſhall not be poſſible for any other Subjects to exceed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>28th.</hi> was preſented to His Majeſty the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> of the City of <hi>Bristol;</hi> acknowledging, promiſing, and wiſhing much after the manner as thoſe before.</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>18th.</hi> was Preſented the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> acknowledging, promiſing and wiſhing like their preceeding Brethren; acknowledging the King, though a <hi>(Zealous Papist)</hi> yet the <hi>most tender and affectionate Prince that ever ſway'd the Scepter of His Empire;</hi> out-doing <hi>all expectation and deſert of His Subjects;</hi> promiſing <hi>Submiſſion to Him under God,</hi> and <hi>that unfeignedly, in all things commanded them by Him;</hi> Praying that God may grant Him <hi>whatſoever may be needful,</hi> for His then preſent and future Happineſs.</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> was Preſented to His Majeſty the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> of <hi>Middleſex, Hertford, Bucks, Oxon, Warwick, Northampton, Lincoln, Huntington, Bedford, Cambridge, Eſſex, Kent Surry, Suſſex, Southampton</hi> and <hi>Dorſet-ſhires,</hi> Confirming with very Hyperbolical Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, all things afore promiſed and owned by the reſt of Their preceding Brethren.</p>
            <p>And after all theſe was preſented, yet one more Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> of <hi>Oxford, Abbington,</hi> and <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> with the ſame Flatteries and Warranties as their Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. They had once afore Addreſſed in that of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152569:7"/>Counties of <hi>Oxon</hi> and <hi>Berks:</hi> But it ſeems theſe <hi>Anabaptisto-Papists</hi> could not reſt ſo without a peculiar application, ſo proud it ſeems they were of their Intereſt in a Popiſh Prince.</p>
            <p>And by all theſe Addreſſes, it appears plainly, that not only the moſt part, if not all the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> in and about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but all over <hi>England,</hi> have voluntarily and freely engaged themſelves unto their utmoſt to aid and aſſiſt King <hi>James</hi> in taking off the <hi>Test</hi> and all <hi>Poenal Laws;</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to open the ancient Floud gates of Stoppage, and to let in an Inundation of Popery, to over-run and drown not only the <hi>Church of England,</hi> but alſo the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, with an overflow of Popiſh Oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>Now true it is, that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is a matter not reaſonably of any Power to be denied unto any of its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and cannot be ſpoken againſt. But <hi>Liberty of Schiſm</hi> is quite another thing, and ſuch as Holy Writ utterly Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors. It is the will of God [<hi>that all Chriſtians be of one mind, Eph.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.] And we know what an <hi>heinous thing</hi> it was eſteemed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> [That <hi>there were Diviſions in the Church, the Members dividing and ſeparating into Parties,</hi> (ver. 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)] And theſe things both Magiſtrates and Miniſters ought to remedy to the beſt of their skill. And in Old times they were always eſteemed <hi>good Kings</hi> who puniſhed <hi>Innovations</hi> in Religion, and that with Severity. And the Apoſtles in the <hi>New Testament</hi> were as urgent to the ſame purpoſe, [to reject all <hi>Hereticks,</hi> (<hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10.2 <hi>Joh.</hi> ver. 9, 10, 11. and 3 <hi>Joh.</hi> ver. 9, 10.)] Such <hi>Paul</hi> accurſeth, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.) And wiſheth ſuch Perverters who <hi>trouble the Church,</hi> that they might <hi>be cut off,</hi> (<hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.)</p>
            <p>Conſider we therefore, that the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> being a perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſort of People, dangerous both to Church and State, wherever they have crept into Power: As was manifeſt at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and after at <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſince in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in times of the late Rebellion: And are a Sect that do hold Dectrines deſtructive to the Peace of Church and State, denying the Power of the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> in many things;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152569:7"/>and do maintain <hi>a Church againſt a Church,</hi> and <hi>Altar against Altar</hi> in the ſame Church; and ſet up <hi>Lay Preachers,</hi> and maintain <hi>Re-baptizing.</hi> All which Doctrines, being by the General Councils in pureſt Primitive times <hi>Forbidden,</hi> and <hi>Accurſed</hi> and declared to be <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> and <hi>Haeretical,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be called matters of Conſcience, no more than <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Fornication</hi> can be ſo called. Againſt <hi>Re baptizing,</hi> ſee <hi>Can.</hi> 4. <hi>Apost.</hi> and <hi>Can. Prim. Carthag.</hi> confirmed by the <hi>[Can. Secund. Concil. Oecumen. Constant.]</hi> againſt <hi>Lay-Preachers,</hi> and <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Altar againſt Altar,</hi> ſee <hi>Can.</hi> 16, and 17. <hi>Concil. Millev.</hi> and all the <hi>firſt ſix General Councils.</hi> Now what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is Condemned by any of the Six, or at leaſt Four firſt General Councils, cannot be maintained as matter of Conſcience, it being plain matter of Schiſm. And all <hi>Schiſm</hi> is by the Magiſtrate to be puniſhed equally with Murther and Adultery, and therefore not to be Tolerated. And yet we ſee how friendly theſe Haereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the <hi>Anabaptiſts and Papists</hi> do Hug each other; no Hand and Glove did ever better fit one the other.</p>
            <p>It was ſix Weeks after the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> e'er any other Sect advanced, the poor Men of the <hi>West</hi> only excepted, (who being Pardoned their Lives, had juſt cauſe to be thankful.) But Thouſands of their Fellows had not that opportunity. And yet on <hi>April</hi> the <hi>30th</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> came in altogether of a Cluſter: Whereof the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> marched in the Front, whoſe Humble Addreſs was preſented to His Majeſty, by the name of <hi>Several Miniſters of the Goſpel in and about the City of</hi> London, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called</hi> Presbyterians; Who <hi>[Acknowledging with great joy, His Majeſties Royal bounty and Chriſtian judgment, and Fatherly inclination to Them, and Their juſt ſecurity under His Protection: And promiſing with a conſtant Emulation, that They will ſtrive to be moſt forward and faithful, in Their Allegiance to His Perſon and Crown;</hi> do wiſh and pray <hi>He may enjoy a long Reign over Them.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> were forward in their Promiſes, but theſe appear as it were their <hi>Rivals,</hi> ſtriving to outdo them. At the ſame time alſo was Preſented the [<hi>Humble Addreſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152569:8"/>of Their Brethren and Kinsfolks of</hi> Weſtminſter.] Who the Place and ſtile conſidered, do evidence theſe <hi>Anonymous</hi> Addreſſers to have been Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> and his Flock, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the Addreſe, ſpake as follows, <hi>[Oh, that we had but Windows in our Hearts, that Your Majeſty might ſee our Loyalty!]</hi> Beſpeaking themſelves much to the ſame purpoſe with the <hi>London Presbyters,</hi> but in a more gilded Stile and Hyperbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Language, do promiſe high both by <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours,</hi> to contrive <hi>a moſt bleſſed Union</hi> between the King and His <hi>Papists</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Themſelves</hi> on the other; Which things ſeriouſly weighed; read but their <hi>Promiſes and Subſcriptions,</hi> and then who will be judge, let him ſpeak but plain truth, and ſo tell who are in earneſt thoſe Men (whatever they give out) who are for the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in again of King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> and a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! Or if not, then ſay at leaſt what pitiful Flatterers have been thoſe <hi>London Presbyterians, Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Loyal Subjects of Weſtminster,</hi> but Men of a <hi>Punick Faith,</hi> no more to be believed than the Impoſtor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who by his Golden Promiſes drew in a third part of the World to be his <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> in expectation of his coming at a <hi>Thouſand years end,</hi> to give them the Rule all over the World! But his day being long ſince come and gone, the good Man forgetting his Word, fell faſt aſleep, and his Faith became tranſmigrated into a very Lie. And ſuch was the Faith of theſe doubty <hi>Presbyterians</hi> unto King <hi>James,</hi> when he ſtood moſt in need of them.</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> was preſented <hi>The Humble Thanks of ſeveral Subjects of</hi> Exon <hi>and the County of</hi> Devon, <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts:</hi> Acknowledging His Majeſty, <hi>Their free, Gracious and wonderful Deliverer:</hi> Declaring that <hi>They had no hand in the Rebellion of</hi> 85. And <hi>that they do heartily hate that, and all Rebellion upon any pretence whatſoever. That they are thankful for the Liberty given by the Declaration of Indulgence the</hi> 4th. <hi>of</hi> April, 1687. And <hi>do promiſe all due Obedience; and pray for God's greatest Bleſſings on His Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now all other Addreſſers were wont to ſay in their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes what Perſwaſion they were of: Only the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152569:8"/>as if aſhamed to appear plainly courting <hi>Popery,</hi> in many of their firſt Addreſſes concealed their name of <hi>Presbyterian.</hi> But by the name <hi>Noncon,</hi> almoſt proper to that Sect alone, and by the <hi>Stile,</hi> we humbly conceive what theſe Addreſſers were; the Brethren of Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and lineally Deſcended from that Generation of the <hi>Aſſembly of</hi> 48, who held King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, while the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> cut off His Head: And yet loe how demurely they can <hi>wipe their Mouths</hi> like the <hi>Whore in the Proverbs,</hi> (Ch. 30.20.) ſaying, <hi>they have done no hurt,</hi> and how much they <hi>abhor Rebellion upon any pretence whatſoever;</hi> while at the ſame time it is the known Principle of thoſe of that Perſwaſion, <hi>That their Kings may be Excommunicated, called to account,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and Executed. See <hi>Buch. de jure Regni,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>21ſt.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of the Nonconforming Loyal Subjects of</hi> New-Caſtle <hi>upon</hi> Tyne. Acknowledging wonderful Thanks for His Majeſties <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;</hi> ſtiling him <hi>a Peaceably diſpoſed Prince,</hi> and promiſing <hi>cheerful and dutiful Obedience to Him, and to ſerve Him at their utmoſt Hazard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of the Diſſenting Subjects of</hi> Taunton <hi>in</hi> Somerſet-ſhire:] Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging His Majeſties <hi>Indulgence to be a greater Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them to Duty and Allegiance, than all the Oaths, Teſts and Subſcriptions that could have been Impoſed:</hi> Promiſing <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall never repent of thoſe Favours to them:</hi> And wiſhing and praying, that <hi>all the Bleſſings of Heaven may for ever Crown His Sacred Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May the 28th.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Hamble Addreſs of the Presbyterians of</hi> Briſtol;] proclaiming their <hi>Acquaintance with His Majeſty, of Old, and before He came to the Crown, and how in thoſe days, He had promiſed His intentions of Indulgence to them:</hi> Declaring <hi>that they queſtion not in the leaſt His reſolution to preſerve this their Happineſs with the injoyments of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, according to the aſſurances of His Declaration, ſince they knew it to proceed from a mature Judgment, and a Principle root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in His Majeſty:</hi> And promiſing to <hi>out-do all</hi> Men <hi>of their Capacity, in all ſuch things which have a tendency towards the promoting the Peace and Proſperity of His Majeſties Reign:</hi> And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152569:9"/>praying for Him with imploring words, <hi>that His Majeſties ſelf and Family,</hi> (viz. <hi>The Prince of</hi> Wales) <hi>may abound with the beſt of Bleſſings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Loe we, what a Diſcovery is here confeſſed out of this Addreſs, of a Confoederacy between the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> of long ſtanding, in order to promote the King's <hi>Declaration of Indulgence,</hi> for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> or rather of the common Schiſms that both thoſe Sects are guilty of. But who will think that theſe <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of <hi>Briſtol</hi> were the only Men of ſuch Confoederacy, without their Brethren of <hi>London!</hi> And if not, then let any reaſonable Man be judge who they are that are for the bringing in again of King, <hi>James,</hi> and not only ſo, but are obliged by promiſe ſo to do; and have no ways to diſengage themſelves unto him left, but by proclaiming themſelves the greateſt <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors</hi> in nature, the loudeſt <hi>Liars</hi> and verieſt <hi>Vilains</hi> living: For it is manifeſt to all the Kingdom, that how much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in King <hi>James</hi>'s time the Properties were Invaded of the Church of <hi>England</hi> men, yet thoſe of the <hi>Presbyterians, Anabaptiſts, Quakers, Independents, Roman-Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Popiſh-Churchmen,</hi> were never ſtirred.</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of the Presbyterians of</hi> Norwich.] In all acknowledgments, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations and Promiſes, ſtriving to overdo their Brethren of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> concluding and heartily crying with one Voice, <hi>[Let the King live for ever.]</hi> whence ſay we with Admiration, Oh what a great King <hi>James</hi> man was this <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> or elſe he was as great an <hi>Impoſtor!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Jame</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of the Loyal Subjects of</hi> Teverton <hi>in</hi> Devon-ſhire; (that is, the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians</hi> there) in all things concurring with their Brethren of <hi>Norwich,</hi> only in variety of new Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ſomewhat different.]</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of ſeveral Benchers and Barriſters of the</hi> Middle-Temple.] Giving Thanks for the <hi>Gracious Declaration for Toleration,</hi> and <hi>aſſerting His Majeſties Royal Prerogative,</hi> and <hi>wiſhing him a long, happy and glorious Reign.</hi> But what were theſe Lawyers? Not <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> nor <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſure, <hi>Presbyterians</hi> they might be, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152569:9"/>ſome <hi>Papiſts.</hi> We have only hinted the matter of Fact. And rarely can be found any Divided Party without ſome Lawyers among them, eſpecially where a Cauſe is Thriving.</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of the Subjects of</hi> Plymouth, <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> wherein appears a concurrence with their Brethren in all Acknowledgments, Promiſes and Wiſhes, and words, only in different Language.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of many Thouſand Citizens of</hi> Coventry.] Much to the ſame purpoſe with thoſe of <hi>Plymouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the ſame time alſo was preſented [<hi>The Humble Addreſs of the Merchants and conſiderable Traders of</hi> Exon.] Theſe alſo (<hi>Noncons,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) Giving great Thanks for the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Indulgence, did unanimouſly declare as the Reſolution of one Man, that when ever His Majesties Occaſions ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it; That the utmoſt drop of their Bloud, and expence of their Fortunes ſhould be at His Majeſties diſpoſe;</hi> and concluded <hi>Wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Imploring God Almighty, that ſo Wiſe, Pious and Juſt a Monarch may be a long Ruler and Conſervator in Peace and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, of the Kingdoms and Dominions belonging to His Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the ſame time alſo, much to the ſame purpoſe, was preſented the [<hi>Humble Addreſs of the Protestant Diſſenting Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of</hi> Berwick <hi>upon</hi> Tweed. And of the <hi>Loyal Diſſenting</hi> Subjects of <hi>Marlborough</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>20th.</hi> the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Miniſters</hi> and <hi>their Congregations,</hi> in and about <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was preſented to King <hi>James,</hi> being Tranſmitted to Him by the Lord Deputy the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> a fierce <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and againſt the Law put in place, without taking the <hi>Test.</hi> Notwithſtanding theſe pretended <hi>Proteſtants</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> in order to Support their ſinful Schiſm of <hi>Factious Conventions,</hi> by maintaining <hi>Altar againſt Altar,</hi> againſt the Good <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Holy General Councils,</hi> did ſhamefully comply with the moſt deſigning <hi>Papiſts,</hi> againſt all Laws of God and man, to trample under foot both Law and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; Flattering the King's Majeſty like their Fellows in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152569:10"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> with their Hyperbolick thanks for His Suppreſſing the good Laws of the Kingdom, and promiſing to ſtand by Him with encouragements <hi>paſt room for fear in His Royal Breast.</hi> And yet loe, how much it is ſince come to paſs, that through the Treachery of theſe Promiſes His Flattered and Deluded Majeſty hath been utterly overwhelmed with endleſs Fears, and deſperate Hopes.</p>
            <p>On <hi>June</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> was preſented the <hi>Humble Addreſs of ſeveral Diſſenting Miniſters,</hi> that is, <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of the Weſt part of <hi>Somerſet-ſhire,</hi> proclaiming His Majeſties <hi>tranſcendent Goodneſs,</hi> and wiſhing him the <hi>Choicest of all Bleſſings in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth;</hi> (that is, never to be interrupted in His Reign by His Highneſs the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> or any other Mortal breathing) but <hi>that His Reign may be long and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous,</hi> and to be <hi>had in remembrance to all Generations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> was preſented the <hi>Humble and Thankful Addreſs of the moſt Loyal Subjects,</hi> (that is, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) of <hi>Kings-bridge</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> Thanking and Promiſing like their Fellows.</p>
            <p>And on <hi>July</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> was preſented another of the fame from the <hi>Loyal Subjects, (Nonconforming Presbyterians)</hi> in and about <hi>York.</hi> And another of the ſame from thoſe of <hi>Malden, Cogſhal, Chelmsford, Braintree, Witham,</hi> and <hi>Halſted</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> This was ſtuffed with very much of affected Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: Acknowledging <hi>Miraculous Providences preſerving His Majeſty by Sea and Land, as it were on purpoſe to ſuppreſs and ſtifle the good Laws of this Kingdom:</hi> Which act agreeing with theſe Mens Luſts, though againſt the Wiſdom and Senſe of the whole Kingdom met in Parliament, theſe do ſtile to <hi>do great Services deſigned of the Almighty to be done by Him.</hi> And this they ſtile <hi>the moſt Melodious Harp to Charm all evil Spirits, that many other Princes had no skill to uſe,</hi> &amp;c. Which Paſſages whether they ſavor more of affected Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, or of a ſort of Blaſphemous Flattery, by calling <hi>Good, Evil,</hi> or <hi>Evil, Good,</hi> I leave to the Readers Cenſure.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> was preſented <hi>[The Humble Addreſs of the Loyal Subjects (or Presbyterians)</hi> of <hi>Wellingborough, Kette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Rothwell, Wellford</hi> and <hi>Creaton</hi> in <hi>Northampton-ſhire.] Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152569:10"/>Admiring, Flattering,</hi> &amp;c. as the reſt: But eſpecially magnifying <hi>His Majeſties Royal word,</hi> though he was a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and promiſing to men <hi>by Papiſts, reputed Hereticks,</hi> as the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> unalterable.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> the <hi>17th.</hi> were preſented three <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, whereof one from <hi>South Molton,</hi> and another from <hi>Aſhburton</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> and a third from the Shire Town of <hi>Northampton,</hi> Promiſing after the old rate, excepting that that from <hi>Northampton</hi> kept more within compaſs of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration than any which had gone before.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> came in the <hi>Humble Addreſs of the Loyal Subjects,</hi> (otherwiſe <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) <hi>of the Province of</hi> Munſter <hi>in</hi> Ireland, Tranſmitted by the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel.</hi> And another from the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Both full of Flatteries as before.</p>
            <p>On <hi>July the 26th.</hi> was preſented from the <hi>Noncon</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Lanca-ſhire,</hi> the like Flattering Addreſs to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. And on the <hi>30th.</hi> of the ſame, came in another of the <hi>Noncons</hi> of the Wapentake of <hi>Loynſdale</hi> in the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, alſo ſtufft with the like Flatteries. And on <hi>August</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> came in the like from the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of <hi>Colchester;</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to <hi>anſwer His Majesties tranſcendent Grace toward them, with as constant Obedience towards Him:</hi> Wiſhing and Praying for <hi>all the Divine Beatitudes of God,</hi> to be poured on His Majeſty and Royal Family.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>9th.</hi> was preſented the [<hi>Humble Addreſs of all the</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Miniſters in</hi> Scotland] Promiſing to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Loyal Subjects,</hi> yea though againſt all their Practices and Principles to the contrary, the King being at the ſame time a known Papiſt.</p>
            <p>On <hi>August</hi> the <hi>13th.</hi> came in the <hi>Addreſs of the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Diſſenters of</hi> Plymouth: Acknowledging and Promiſing much after the rate of thoſe of <hi>Eſſex</hi> Mart Towns. And another at the ſame time from <hi>Sheffeild</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire;</hi> not without its Flatteries. Another <hi>Aug. 18th.</hi> of the ſame Stamp from <hi>Cockermouth</hi> in <hi>Cumberland.</hi> And another at the ſame time from <hi>Leathward</hi> in the ſame County. But that of the Diſſenting Merchants and Trades-men in and about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> exceeded at the ſame time, exceeded for Flattery and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152569:11"/>Blaſphemy; comparing King <hi>James</hi> a known <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prince, to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and our <hi>Poenal Laws,</hi> to the Yoak, Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Bondage of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> and worſe than that. And that of the <hi>Dutiful and Obedient Subjects of Chicheſter;</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Act of Indulgence</hi> with the greateſt acts of Wiſdom, and extolling it unto the Skies. And that of the Freemen of <hi>Bath, Auguſt</hi> the <hi>22d.</hi> Acknowledging the Kings undoubted Prerogative by His <hi>Gracious Declaration</hi> to ſtifle the force of Law, which they call <hi>conſiſtent with true Piety;</hi> were notoriouſly Flattering.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> was preſented the conceited <hi>Humble Addreſs</hi> of the <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Romſey, Ringwood, Fordingbridge</hi> and <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> in <hi>Hant-ſhire,</hi> fond and full of Flattery.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> was brought forth the Addreſs of <hi>Worceſter Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> and of the <hi>Maſter-Builders</hi> and other Artificers about <hi>London.</hi> And of the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> about <hi>Shrewsbury.</hi> And of the <hi>Peaceable Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>Namptwich, Wem,</hi> and <hi>Whit-church</hi> in <hi>Shrop-ſhire.</hi> And of the <hi>Protestant Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>Oſweſtree</hi> in the ſame County. All beſpeaking the Common Language of their Fellows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> came forth the Addreſſes of the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of <hi>Cheſter.</hi> Of the Loving (Subjects, called <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) of <hi>Macclesfeild.</hi> And <hi>September</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> of the Loyal Subjects the <hi>Stroudwater Clothiers</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire.</hi> And of the Free-men of the Borough of <hi>Banbury,</hi> and of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Dorcheſter.</hi> And <hi>September</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>Oxford-ſhire.</hi> And on <hi>September</hi> the <hi>15th.</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Derby</hi> and <hi>Nottingham</hi>-Shires: All full of Flattery, and promiſing dutiful Obedience.</p>
            <p>On <hi>September</hi> the <hi>22d.</hi> came out the Addreſs of the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Edenburg</hi> and <hi>Canongate,</hi> ſtarting this New Doctrine, that <hi>there is no inconſiſtency betwixt true Loyalty and Presbyterian Principles,</hi> &amp;c. And yet time hath ſince ſhewn the quite contrary from the ſame Miniſters. On <hi>September</hi> the <hi>29th.</hi> the thankful Addreſs of the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> the <hi>Devizes, Cane, Chippenham, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, Warmiſter, Throw-bridge</hi> and <hi>Bradford</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi> All ſpeaking after the ſame Canting way of flattery. The</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152569:11"/>
            <p>The Humble Addreſs of the Electors of <hi>Ladgeſhal</hi> in <hi>Wilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> at the ſame time promiſed <hi>always to chooſe ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as ſhould be Faithful and Serviceable to the Crown;</hi> that is, unto the <hi>Popiſh Intereſt,</hi> the King being a known Papiſt. At the ſame time alſo the Addreſſes of the Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Andover, Whit-church</hi> and <hi>Clotford,</hi> beſpeak the old Language of Flattery. And that of the Subjects of <hi>Ciren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire,</hi> coming forth at the ſame time, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to <hi>chooſe ſuch Members as ſhall comply with His Majeſty in putting down</hi> Poenal Laws, and by conſequence promote <hi>Popery.</hi> Alſo at the ſame time the Addreſs of the <hi>Noncons</hi> of <hi>Reading, Abbington</hi> and <hi>Newbury.</hi> And another of the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> of <hi>Nottingham.</hi> Alſo <hi>October</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> the Addreſs of the Loyal Subjects the <hi>Combers, Weavers, and other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire.</hi> Alſo <hi>October</hi> the <hi>17th.</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters</hi> and their Congregation in <hi>Eaſt Somerſet-ſhire, Bath, Shipton, Froom Bruton, Wincaunton, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, Frary, Inſcomb.</hi> And another from the <hi>truly Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Honiton</hi> in <hi>Devon-ſhire.</hi> Alſo another from the <hi>Loyal Subjects of Pembrook, Carmarthen, Cardigan,</hi> and the Town of <hi>Swanzey</hi> in <hi>Glamorgan-ſhire, Presbyterian Miniſters, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts, with their Congregations.</hi> Alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Dutiful Subjects, <hi>the Noncons of Kingſton upon Thames.</hi> Alſo another from the <hi>Dutiful Diſſenting Subjects of Cambridge.</hi> Alſo another from the <hi>Presbyterian Subjects of Hull,</hi> and of two numerous Congregations there. Alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother from <hi>Weobly</hi> in <hi>Hereford ſhire.</hi> Alſo another from the the Loyal and Faithful Subjects of <hi>Portsmouth.</hi> All pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing Mountains of Obedience, and extolling His Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; whereof thoſe of <hi>Hull</hi> and <hi>Weobly</hi> do much exceed. On <hi>October</hi> the <hi>24th.</hi> followed the Addreſſes of the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of King</hi>'s <hi>Lynne,</hi> and of the <hi>Noncon Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Dorſet-ſhire.</hi> And on <hi>November</hi> the <hi>3d.</hi> the Impatient, but moſt Loyal Subjects, the Free holders and others of <hi>Chard</hi> in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire.</hi> On <hi>November the 14th.</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of <hi>Maidſtone.</hi> On <hi>November</hi> the <hi>21ſt.</hi> the <hi>Diſſenting Subjects</hi> of <hi>Lewes</hi> in <hi>Suſſex;</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenting</hi> Subjects of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> And of the Obedient <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>Tenter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152569:12"/>Cranbrok,</hi> and <hi>Staplehurſt</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> On <hi>December the 1ſt.</hi> the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel in New-England,</hi> and the <hi>Loyal Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Hertford,</hi> did bring forth their ſeveral Addreſſes of Thanks, and promiſes of Obedience, and all poſſible good Wiſhes: Whereof thoſe of <hi>Hertford</hi> promiſed to chooſe Members for Parliament as ſhould be acceptable to His Majeſty, and ſupporters of His Prerogative.</p>
            <p>On <hi>December</hi> the <hi>15th.</hi> ſeveral Miniſters <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter-ſhire,</hi> were the laſt which preſented their Flattering Addreſs unto His Majeſty King <hi>James</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>Now theſe <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are a new Sect of <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> Introduced by Mr. <hi>John Calvin</hi> at <hi>Geneva;</hi> from whence they have ſpread their Doctrines into <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and alſo into <hi>England:</hi> And are ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the Parity of their Clergy, being all <hi>Presbyters,</hi> without any <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Superintendants</hi> among them. And are a People generally affecting Government by a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> and hating Monarchy in the <hi>State</hi> as well as in the <hi>Church.</hi> And as appears by their Writings and Practices, they hold with <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> that <hi>Kings may be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated and Depoſed;</hi> and in caſe of a Corrupt Prince, they hold Rebellion to be no Crime. [<hi>Buchanan de jure Regni,</hi> and the <hi>practices of the late Wars of the Parliament,</hi> 1641. againſt their King, <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt.]</p>
            <p>The firſt who attempted to introduce this <hi>Presbyterian Schiſm,</hi> was <hi>Aerius,</hi> who was therefore Branded by the Church for a <hi>Schiſmatick:</hi> But being nipp'd in the Bud, in thoſe days he had no Diſciples. Howbeit this <hi>Presbyterianiſm</hi> is a Rent from the Church, oppoſing all the Six firſt <hi>General Councils,</hi> which do <hi>forbid any</hi> Presbyter <hi>in contempt of his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, to gather any ſeparate Congregation of his own,</hi> [Can. <hi>Apoſt.</hi> xxxii.] <hi>Nicaeni Concil.</hi> Can. 16. <hi>Arelatens Concil.</hi> Can. 19. <hi>Gangren. Concil.</hi> Can. 6. <hi>Antiochen. Concil.</hi> Can. 5. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginens. Concil.</hi> ii. Can. 11.] And <hi>forbid any Biſhop to be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained without three Biſhops,</hi> and any <hi>Presbyter or Deacon to be Ordained without one Biſhop preſent,</hi> [<hi>Nicaeni Concil,</hi> ii. Can 4. Can. 6. Can. <hi>Apoſt.</hi> 1, 2, 7.] <hi>Ant. Concil.</hi> Can. 9. The Canons of theſe <hi>General Councils</hi> of the Holy Primitive times, are the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152569:12"/>Bonds of the Church, which whoſoever breaks, is a <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick.</hi> And there can be no pretence of Conſcience to juſtifie <hi>Schiſm:</hi> but the Magiſtrate ought to puniſh it. And though <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> ought to be allowed, yet no Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>Schiſm.</hi> And though in caſe the Magiſtrate ſhall diſpenſe with the puniſhment of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and we know not under God, who ſhall call him to account for ſuch Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: Yet is it a ſin which God will certainly Puniſh; and therefore woe be unto thoſe Flatterers who in ſuch Caſes, <hi>do call Evil Good, and Good, Evil!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next after that of the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> was Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the ſame day <hi>April</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> 1687. [<hi>The Humble and Thankful Addreſs of the King's Subjects,</hi> commonly called <hi>Quakers, in and about the City of</hi> London.] And theſe alſo glory in it, that they were of Cabinet Council with the King, acknowledging that <hi>They were privy to the deſign of the Declaration for Liberty, long before it came forth;</hi> and with great joy declare <hi>Their Thanks, that they have ſuch a King of ſuch a Principle,</hi> promiſing Him <hi>always to approve themſelves His faithful and loving Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And on <hi>May</hi> the <hi>25th.</hi> came forth [<hi>The Humble and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acknowledgment of the peaceable Subjects called Quakers in this Kingdom, from their uſual Yearly Meeting in</hi> London, <hi>the 19th. day of the</hi> Third Month, <hi>Vulgarly called</hi> May, 1687. Beſpeaking in all things as the former, in the name of the <hi>Quakers</hi> all over <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>June the 18th.</hi> came forth [<hi>The grateful Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the People called</hi> Quakers <hi>of</hi> Scotland] Proclaiming <hi>God's wonderful Providence, who made the King's retiring into their Country give an happy turn to His Affairs, to the Defeating the Deſigns of His Enemies;</hi> acknowledging <hi>His great Kindneſſes to them, for favouring them in</hi> 1679. And ſo proceeding in <hi>Hyperbolical Thankfulneſs,</hi> they conclude with promiſes of Obedience. On <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>18th.</hi> much after the ſame rate was brought in from the <hi>Quakers</hi> of the Weſt of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And on <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>26th.</hi> came the like from the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Tranſmitted to the King by the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> the Lord Deputy there. On <hi>September</hi> the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152569:13"/>
               <hi>29th.</hi> (the King being in His Progreſs) the [<hi>Hearty welcome and humble Salutation of the peaceable Subjects, called Quakers, of</hi> Wales <hi>and the North Weſt of</hi> England.] Beſpeaking in their Canting way their welcome of him into thoſe Parts; their joy of Him, and promiſes of Obedience. And ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo came in the [<hi>Humble Congratulation of the peaceable Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of</hi> Briſtol, <hi>called</hi> Quakers;] beſpeaking much as the reſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> generally, an Ignorant ſort of People, of uncertain Principles of Religion, and without any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly Confeſſion of Faith, have broached many <hi>old Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies;</hi> and as is apparent, have many hidden <hi>Papiſts</hi> among them, and are thought to be much Popiſhly inclined; and many of them appear as it were Paganiſh, and ſeem as if inſpired with Diabolical Deluſions and Enthuſiaſms; and are a dangerous ſort of <hi>Haereticks,</hi> pretending to be <hi>perfect in Righteouſneſs,</hi> full of the Light of the Spirit, do much debaſe if not deny the uſe of God's holy Ordinances, pretending to be above them: And therefore plainly appearing to be a People <hi>void of all Conſcience, damnable Haereticks:</hi> And yet theſe alſo under pretence of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> muſt have Liberty to ſow their <hi>Tares of Haereſies</hi> all over the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and boaſt themſelves as the great Confidents of King <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Second.</hi> And among the reſt of the <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> Voted for the <hi>Old Members</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and were of the number of thoſe Upbraiders of the New Members, <hi>[That they would bring in King James again.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> on the ſame day, <hi>April</hi> the <hi>30th.</hi> 1687. came forth the Humble Addreſs of the Loyal Subjects of the <hi>Congregational Perſwaſion,</hi> (otherwiſe called <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants</hi>) in and about the City of <hi>London.</hi> Acknowledging His Majeſties Declaration a <hi>Tranſcendent and Unparallel'd favour, promiſing their conſtant Endeavour</hi> to anſwer His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties juſt Expectations from them, (that is, to chooſe <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament</hi> for His Majeſties Intereſt) Approving themſelves in Inclination as well as Duty, His Majeſties moſt Loyal Subjects.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152569:13"/>
            <p>Theſe were the chief and prime actors in the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, as the Principal deſigners in the whole Tragedy: And yet now to ſee to, are as Zealous to make amends for all their Regicide, by a moſt firm Affection and Diligence to maintain His Son in all His Popiſh Deſigns, as from their own Profeſſion is moſt plainly ſignified.</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>14th.</hi> the [<hi>Gratulatory Addreſs of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Congregational Perſwaſion of the City of</hi> Norwich] was preſented to His Majeſty; Acknowledging Him <hi>Placed on the Throne of this Realm by the moſt High God, as Natural, Legal, and Rightful King,</hi> (it ſeems notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding His being a Zealous <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and violently Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing againſt the known Laws of the Land;) yet <hi>in the whole courſe of his Reign a Wiſe and Merciful King.</hi> Alſo acknowledging that <hi>they are for Monarchy, as the only An cient, Legal and Rightful Government of this Nation.</hi> (It is to be remembred, that theſe were the late <hi>Oliverians,</hi> who turned out the <hi>Rump,</hi> to ſet up the <hi>Protector.</hi>) That His Majeſty hath taken care as a <hi>Common Father, for the good of all his People:</hi> Wherefore they ſhall adhere unto him as their King, with all Loyalty, Fidelity and hearty Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to their power.</p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>17th.</hi> was Publiſhed the Addreſs of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> together: of which already ſaid in the <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> Addreſs for <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe <hi>Independents</hi> either ſpake truth from their Hearts, or Diſſembled: If the laſt, Then who ſhall believe them hereafter? If the firſt, Then they are ſtill in their Hearts for the bringing in of King <hi>James</hi> again. And if ſo, why then upbraided they the <hi>New Members</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> lately Nominated, that they would bring him in? But will they ſay they are Changed, yet muſt they go for Impoſtors and falſe Villains; for King <hi>James</hi> kept fair with them to the laſt, however he Oppreſt the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But what can we expect from the <hi>Sons of Murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</hi> They ſmell of the Bloud of the <hi>Father;</hi> they are falſe to the <hi>Son,</hi> and cannot be true to the <hi>Grand-child.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152569:14"/>And it's to be fear'd in the end will be found falſe to their own <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> the <hi>28th.</hi> came forth the Joynt Addreſs of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Briſtol:</hi> which has been mentioned before in the Addreſſes of <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> And on <hi>June</hi> the <hi>11th.</hi> appeared another Addreſs of the <hi>Loyal Subjects of the Congregational Perſwaſion</hi> dwelling in <hi>Ipſwich, Eury</hi> St. <hi>Edmunds,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Suffolk:</hi> Acknowledging King <hi>James</hi> to be their <hi>Covering Cherub; under whoſe refreſhing Shadow they promiſe themſelves Reſt: Promiſing truly to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve therefore the Intereſt of His Majeſties Power and Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> Which in plain terms, was as much as to ſay, <hi>[The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Popiſh Religion.]</hi> At the ſame time alſo was Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Moſt Dutiful and Loyal Subjects of the Congregational Perſwaſion of</hi> Great Yarmouth <hi>in</hi> Norfolk. Acknowledging, Praiſing, promiſing, and Praying, as their Fellows before them. On <hi>July</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> became Publick the <hi>Humble Addreſs of the Loyal Subjects of the Congregational Perſwaſion of</hi> Bidford <hi>in</hi> Devonſhire. And another <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> of the ſame, of the <hi>Norfolkſhire</hi>-men. And another <hi>September</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian and Congregational Nonconformiſts of</hi> Macclesfeild in <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire.</hi> And another <hi>September</hi> the <hi>29th,</hi> of the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Perſwaſion</hi> of the <hi>Counties of North Wales</hi> and <hi>Shrews<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi> And <hi>October the 17th.</hi> another of the ſame, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Pembroke, Caermarthen, Cardigan</hi> and <hi>Swanſey,</hi> in <hi>Glamorganſhire.</hi> And <hi>November</hi> the <hi>14th. Another</hi> of <hi>the ſame</hi> from <hi>Hitching</hi> and <hi>Hertford</hi> in <hi>Hertford-ſhire.</hi> All beſpeaking much to the ſame purpoſe, in extolling the Vertue and Wiſdom of King <hi>James,</hi> and promiſing Him their utmoſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in furtherance of His Deſigns. Only this laſt more expreſly promiſes, <hi>to do their utmoſt that ſuch Perſons may be choſen to ſit in Parliament as will concur with His Majeſty that Liberty may be ſetled by an unalterable Law, and that His Majeſty may be the greateſt Monarch on Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such was the Senſe of theſe <hi>Independent Addreſſes.</hi> Now theſe <hi>Independents</hi> are a ſort of <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> adhering
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152569:14"/>partly with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and partly with the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> and in a middle way between both, are a ſort of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> who denying the power of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution of Churches,</hi> againſt all Orders; of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ſet up Churches in the name of <hi>Themſelves,</hi> dependent upon no other Authority except the <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the People:</hi> And being <hi>Renders of Chriſt's</hi> Seamleſs Coat, ought to have been Suppreſſed: However having nothing of any <hi>caſe of Conſcience</hi> to plead for <hi>Their Schiſms,</hi> ought rather (as men weed out Tares from among their Wheat) to have been rooted up out of God's Church; or at leaſt ought not to have been Cheriſhed, as when the <hi>Tares</hi> are ſuffered to overtop and ſhoulder out the good ſeed. However, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> ought not to have been made a Cloak for <hi>Liberty of Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such were the four firſt <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi> Which four having begun the Work, anon after followed certain <hi>popiſhly inclined Members of the Church of England,</hi> who minding the love of the World more than their Religion they profeſſed, Flattered the King's Majeſty with their <hi>Addreſſes</hi> alſo. The firſt beginners were the <hi>Unanimous Addreſs of the Biſhop, Dean, and Chapter of the Cathedral Church of</hi> Durham, <hi>and the reſt of the Clergy of that Dioeceſs,</hi> on <hi>May</hi> the <hi>17th.</hi> 1687. Acknowledging His <hi>Majeſties favour in promiſing to Protect His Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now His Majeſty by His Declaration of <hi>Toleration,</hi> had broken down the Hedge whereby the Rights of the Church were to be preſerved, and had let in the Wild-Beaſts, the <hi>Swine</hi> to devour the <hi>Grapes,</hi> and the <hi>Kine</hi> to <hi>break down the Boughs,</hi> and the Wild-Boar to <hi>root up the Trees of God</hi>'s <hi>Vineyard;</hi> only the <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. were Protected to ſtand by and look on without Moleſtation, but were to have no power to fray one Cow, or to hunt out one Hog, do they never ſo much Miſchief. Now the truth is, the <hi>Declaration of Indulgence,</hi> was a thing <hi>Inconſiſtent with it ſelf:</hi> That His Majeſty ſhould at once protect and maintain all manner of <hi>Haereticks</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152569:15"/>
               <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> which deſtroy the Church; and yet do as much for the Paſtors of the Flock, who are to defend the Church from ſuch deſtroying Wolves as are the <hi>Haereticks,</hi> &amp;c. That he ſhould at once maintain the <hi>Canons</hi> of <hi>Holy Councils,</hi> which are the true Rights of the Church, and yet at the ſame time maintain all thoſe who break thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> to pieces! And yet loe how theſe tame Cattel come in with their Addreſs to Thank His Majeſty, that in preſerving the <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> He promiſes notwithſtanding, that he will not deſtroy the Houſholder. This was an odd ſort of Flattery; like the Man who meeting his Phyſician, <hi>prayed him not to be angry that he was not yet Sick.</hi> But to gueſs at theſe mens meaning the <hi>Biſhop, Dean, Chapter,</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> among the <hi>Quakers, Anabaptiſts, Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing for the Declaration: It muſt follow that either the Men deſigning in concluſion to turn <hi>Papiſts,</hi> were found alſo among the Addreſſers, in hopes upon the fall of the Church, to ſhare in her Spoils: Or elſe at beſt they were a ſort of timerous Rats, who thinking the Houſe to be falling down, did run between the Legs of the Deſtroyers for Refuge.</p>
            <p>After theſe, came in the Addreſſes of the <hi>Mayor, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Common Council</hi> and <hi>Free-men of the City of Durham;</hi> beſpeaking the very Language of their Right Reverend Biſhop, <hi>May</hi> 28. And at the ſame time was publiſhed the Humble Addreſs of the <hi>Lord Biſhop, the Dean and Prebendaries of the Cathedral Church of Cheſter,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Clergy of the Arch deanries of Chester and Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> &amp;c. Then followed the Addreſs, of the <hi>Mayor, Aldermen,</hi> &amp;c. of <hi>Richmond</hi> and <hi>Cheſter,</hi> the Subjects of the <hi>Right Reverend Father</hi> of thoſe Places. <hi>June 11th.</hi> next follows the <hi>Addreſs of the Biſhop, Dean, Arch Deacon</hi> and <hi>Clergy of the Dioceſs of Lincoln.</hi> (Now to gueſs at the length of <hi>Hercules</hi> by his Foot, we know that ten for one of that Dioeceſs oppoſed the Addreſs; and yet it is called the Addreſs of the <hi>Arch deacons and Clergy;</hi> and ſo it was of ſome of them: And thus it's probable it was alſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152569:15"/>in the Dioeceſs of <hi>Durham</hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi> This <hi>July</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> And on the <hi>5th.</hi> was publick that of the <hi>Dean and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Rippon in York-ſhire.</hi> Then followed that of the <hi>Biſhop and Clergy of the Dioeceſs</hi> of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litchfield, July 9th.</hi> And laſtly, though long firſt, came out the <hi>Addreſs of the Biſhop and Clergy of the Dioceſs of St.</hi> Davids: (that is, of the new made Biſhop, for it ſeems the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Biſhop was not for it) Now all theſe Church-men wrote after one Copy, which was from <hi>Durham.</hi> There was alſo an Addreſs of certain pretended Church-men of the City of <hi>London;</hi> but it was only a name of what was not, by ſome certain pretenders. And indeed all the five <hi>Epiſcopal Addreſſers,</hi> though true <hi>Biſhops,</hi> yet were but pretended Church-men, while they became perfect <hi>Pillars</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, after all the reſt had begun, the ſixth and laſt, and main <hi>Pillar</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> preſented it ſelf, <hi>The Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Addreſs of His Majeſties Roman Catholick Subjects,</hi> which appeared <hi>May</hi> the <hi>28th.</hi> Now, whatever the reſt were, theſe were certainly in earneſt in all their acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, applauſes, promiſes and good wiſhes. But what is moſt remarkable in their Addreſs is, that they ſay, <hi>[That they can do no leſs than thank God and His Majeſty, for ſuch an happy Expedient as His Declaration for Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for the eaſe and comfort of all His loving Subjects.]</hi> Now, it is againſt the profeſt Principles of the <hi>Roman-Catholick Religion</hi> to allow <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> in matters of <hi>Haereſie and Schiſm,</hi> as they do eſteem all <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts, Quakers</hi> and <hi>Independents</hi> to be ſuch. And in truth it is no wonder, that they who count it a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of their Religion to <hi>Aequivocate,</hi> or in plain terms to <hi>Lie for advantage,</hi> can admit it into their practice to comply with the <hi>worſt of Hereticks</hi> in order to carry on their Deſign, in breaking down the good Laws which are the ſence of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> And this they may as aptly conſent to do, as practically to diſſemble themſelves to be <hi>Quakers</hi> among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> among the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> in order to increaſe <hi>Schiſm</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152569:16"/>and <hi>Hereſie</hi> in a ſtrange Church, that they may with the more ſafety eſtabliſh that great <hi>Schiſme</hi> of their own, <hi>Popery.</hi> And thus we find the <hi>Roman-Catholicks,</hi> the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians, Quakers; Independents,</hi> and <hi>Popiſhly inclined Church-men,</hi> all link'd together in as faſt a Bond of Friendſhip, as faith and truth by Vows and Promiſes can tye them together, in furthering the <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Deſign</hi> of Eſtabliſhing <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> upon the Baſis of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and finally to introduce <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after this Foundation laid, wherever any of theſe Six ſorts of <hi>Papiſh Pillar-men</hi> got in to be a <hi>Mayor of a Corporation,</hi> thence immediately followed an Addreſs from <hi>that Corporation,</hi> to the ſame effect as each Sect had afore Addreſſed. But hitherto His Majeſty had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed no Laws, excepting that he had admitted <hi>Popiſh Officers</hi> into the Army, and into other Places of Truſt, for which He pleaded <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> However the <hi>Parliament</hi> then in force, not approving thereof, was Diſſolved af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two Adjournments, and ten Prorogations in effectual, was finally Diſſolved <hi>July 2d.</hi> 1687. Notwithſtanding Neceſſity had no Law; that putting in of <hi>Popiſh Officers</hi> in all Places of Truſt was to be born with. On <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary 12th.</hi> 1686, the Earl of <hi>Clarendon</hi> being Removed, the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> was ſettled Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And on <hi>March 11th. Henry Lord Arundel of Wardour</hi> a Papiſt, was made <hi>Lord Privy Seal.</hi> About the ſame time, or before, the <hi>Earl of Rocheſter,</hi> Uncle to the King's two Daughters, for ſtanding firm to the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> according to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> was removed out of Place from being <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi> and the Place put into Commiſſioners hands Popiſhly inclined: And the Earl of <hi>Sunderland</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> was made Lord Preſident of the Council. On <hi>February 8th.</hi> the Lord <hi>Caſtlemain,</hi> His Majeſties <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> had Audience. But after the <hi>Addreſſes</hi> once began to come in thick, then the King ventur'd to receive a <hi>Publick Ambaſſador from the Pope, with all the Honours and Ceremonies uſually obſerved on the like Occaſion:</hi> This was done at <hi>Windſor,</hi> on <hi>July
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152569:16"/>5th.</hi> 1687. And on <hi>November 11th.</hi> Father <hi>Petre</hi> the King's Confeſſor and Clerk of the Cloſet, was Sworn of His Majeſties Privy-Council, and took his Place at the Board. And on <hi>November 17th.</hi> was publiſhed a Book called, <hi>An Agreement between the Church of England and Church of Rome, Evinced from the Concertation of ſome of her Sons, with their Brethren the Diſſenters.</hi> Such was the Fruit of the <hi>Addreſſes</hi> made by the <hi>Sir Pillars</hi> of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. On <hi>December 11th.</hi> His Majeſty being encouraged by the abundance of <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> began to view the Liſt of His <hi>Juſtices of the Peace</hi> in all the Counties, and of the <hi>Deputy Lieutenants,</hi> and to turn out of Place all ſuch as would not be for His Declaration of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> and for taking off the <hi>Penal Laws and Teſt.</hi> Whence great numbers in all Counties were turned out, and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>popiſhly inclined Perſons,</hi> came into Place. And about the ſame time, or ſoon after, all Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations were Regulated by abſolute Power, and all Men adhering to the Law were turned out, and <hi>Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>popiſhly inclined Perſons</hi> were put in place. And hence it came to paſs that all the Corporations in <hi>London</hi> became Regulated, and filled with <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> whence followed infinite <hi>Addreſſes</hi> from all theſe New <hi>Corporations,</hi> and from all the New Model'd Companies. After this it was that the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners</hi> had been put in power, and had begun to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute great power of Oppreſſion over many of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Conſciencious Subjects. The Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, the Lord <hi>Biſhop of London,</hi> beloved of moſt Men for his Fatherly care of the Church, againſt all Law and Reaſon had been Suſpended. And on <hi>December 10th.</hi> The <hi>Preſident and Fellows of Magdalen Colledge in Oxford,</hi> againſt <hi>all Law and Conſcience</hi> were <hi>decreed</hi> and <hi>pronounced</hi> uncapable of being admitted into any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Dignity.</hi> Theſe by force appointed by the <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> contrary to all Rules of Law, had been turned out of their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds on the <hi>30th.</hi> of <hi>November</hi> before. On <hi>January</hi> the <hi>23d.</hi> was publiſhed <hi>[The King's right of Indulgence in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152569:17"/>Matters, with the Equity thereof Aſſerted. By a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Honour.]</hi> About this time Commiſſioners were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and made Enquiry after all Monies received for Fines, in the caſe of Seditious Meetings called <hi>Conventicles. March</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> was publiſhed a Book called, [<hi>The Legality of the Court held by His Majeſties Commiſſioners Defended:</hi> And alſo <hi>A Defence of the Doctrine and holy Rites of the Roman Catholick Church.</hi> Againſt Dr. <hi>Burnet's Myſtery of Iniquity Unveiled.</hi>] Unto ſuch an height of Popery was the Kingdom aſcended, and all by means of the <hi>Sir Pillars</hi> of Addreſſers; for alas, the Popiſh Intereſt of it ſelf was pitifully inconſiderable: But by the union and conjunction of theſe <hi>Sir Pillars,</hi> it began to look for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midably. And the King preſuming upon the ſtrength of the <hi>Pillars,</hi> was meerly drawn in and encouraged, beyond all His hope at His Coronation, when he firſt promiſed, and then Swore, to defend and maintain the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land. Whence it may be ſafely maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that wherein ſoever His Majeſty hath acted againſt Law, as is now generally alledged, contrary to his Oaths and Promiſes, although the Breach was really His own proper act, yet the greateſt blame thereof, lyes at their Doors, who by pleading Conſcience to do the greateſt Wickedneſs, drew him in to comply with them; and by promiſing to ſtand by and aſſiſt hiw to the laſt Breath, encouraged him to do what otherwiſe in all likelyhood He never had intended. For when it was declared by His Majeſty on <hi>April</hi> the <hi>27th.</hi> 1688, what was <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties further will and pleaſure</hi> concerning His <hi>Declaration of Indulgence,</hi> He ſaid expreſly. <hi>[We are encouraged by mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Addreſſes, and by many other Aſſuances we receive from Our Subjects of all Perſwaſions, as Teſtimonies of their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and Duty, to ſee it preſerved without Diſtinction.]</hi> And in the ſame Declaration he further ſaith, [<hi>In purſuance of this we have been forced to make many Changet both of Civil and Military Officers throughout our Dominions,</hi> &amp;c.] Whence it fully appears, that what by means of the <hi>Addreſſes</hi> and by means of <hi>private Aſſurances</hi> from the Parties Addreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152569:17"/>before the Addreſſes came forth, His Majeſty was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily drawn in to do all thoſe things which are counted ill, ever ſince his Reign. For as may be well obſerved, many Addreſſes do boaſt of a <hi>Confederacy</hi> with His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> as to the ſubſtance matter of their Addreſſes, from before the time of His Majeſties coming to the Crown.</p>
            <p>Hence followed the Orders iſſued forth, directed unto the <hi>Arch biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Clergy,</hi> to read the King's Declaration in all their Provinces, <hi>Dioeceſſes</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> therein. Which thing they humbly conceiving to be a matter againſt the known Laws of the Land, and not fit to be done, ſo many of them as were then in <hi>London,</hi> did <hi>humbly Petition His Majeſty</hi> to be excuſed from ſuch reading, and ſhewed their Reaſons in their <hi>Petition.</hi> But this <hi>Petition</hi> being judged <hi>Scandalous,</hi> the Arch-biſhop, and Biſhops of St. <hi>Aſaph, Ely, Chichester, Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells, Peterborough,</hi> and <hi>Bristol,</hi> were Summoned before the <hi>Lords of the Council,</hi> and after Appearance, were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Tower, June 8th.</hi> but Bailed out, came to their Tryal, and were Acquitted unto the great joy of the People, though to the great Grief of all <hi>Addreſſers.</hi> During theſe times were ſtrict enquiries made after all Miniſters who refuſed to read the King's Declaration in their Churches, by the Lords Commiſſioners for Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Affairs; but the Chancellors in moſt parts delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Returns, farther time was given. But e'er the day appointed came no, a new face of Affairs happen'd. About theſe times alſo came in new <hi>Addreſſes</hi> thick and three-fold, congratulating for the Birth of the <hi>Prince of Wales.</hi> But in theſe <hi>Addreſſes</hi> the ſeveral <hi>Pillars of Popery</hi> appeared not diſtinctly as before: But in all <hi>Corporations, Grand Juries,</hi> and meetings of <hi>Juſtices,</hi> which at that time were fo far Purged, as moſt of them were either <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Popiſhly inclined;</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, Quakers,</hi> or <hi>Independents.</hi> All which promoting the Deſign. Addreſſes innumerable ceaſed not, until the King himſelf Addreſſed beyond Sea. But at length news arrived of His <hi>Highneſs the Prince of Orange</hi> preparing as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152569:18"/>if he would Invade <hi>England;</hi> whence King <hi>James</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately ſmitten with a ſudden aſtoniſhment, ſent for His <hi>Pillars</hi> about him; the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> the <hi>Independents,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> the <hi>Quakers,</hi> the <hi>Roman-Catholicks,</hi> and the <hi>Popiſhly inclined;</hi> who all proteſted, that they believed the <hi>Prince of Wales</hi> to be undoubtedly his Son: And one Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> being Spokeſman for the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> ſpake with great confidence how much they were bound to believe His word; and ſo ſaid they all, and promiſed to aſſiſt him to the utmoſt. Alſo many or moſt of thoſe Miniſters, <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> or <hi>Independent,</hi> who had fled into <hi>Holland</hi> for ſhelter, becauſe of the Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s or the Earl of <hi>Argyle</hi>'s Inſurrections, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they had been concerned, had returned home, and laid themſelves at the King's Foot, and were admitted to kiſs his Hand, and were eſteemed White Boys: Some alſo of the Gentlemen returned and became great Stick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of King <hi>James,</hi> but the preparations from <hi>Holland</hi> damp'd all. For King <hi>James</hi> Drooping in Spirit, all His <hi>Pillars</hi> could not keep up His Heart. For on the laſt or <hi>September</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> was reſtored to his Dioeceſs. On <hi>October</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> came forth the general Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and the Charter was reſtored to the City. On the <hi>5th.</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Commiſſion was Diſſolved.</hi> And on the <hi>12th.</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> had a Commiſſion to reſtore the Rights of <hi>Magdalen Colledge Oxford,</hi> Whence followed the reſtitution and Fellows. On the <hi>17th.</hi> all Rights were reſtored to the Corporations. Hence all the <hi>Pillars of Popery</hi> beginning to reel and totter, on <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> the <hi>5th</hi> His Highneſs the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> Landed. But after ſome face of Reſiſtance for ſome time appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> on <hi>November</hi> the <hi>26th.</hi> His Majeſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>London,</hi> from <hi>Saliſbury.</hi> The <hi>11th.</hi> of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> he privately withdrew from <hi>White-hall.</hi> On the <hi>12th.</hi> the Lord Chancellor was Taken and carried to the <hi>Tower.</hi> On <hi>December</hi> the <hi>16th.</hi> King <hi>James</hi> returned to <hi>White-hall,</hi> and on the next Morning went quite off.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152569:19"/>And His Highneſs the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> came to St. <hi>James</hi>'s. And thus fell flat all the <hi>Sir Pillars of Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe God that Truth may flouriſh, and that</hi> Popery <hi>appear no more. But God's Will be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let all good Men do their Duty; and then Bleſſed ſhall be the Dead who Die in the Lord, and their Works ſhall follow them.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
